Guide to the Max Shachtman Correspondence with Leon Trotsky
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Max Shachtman correspondence with Leon Trotsky
1930-1940
GEN MSS 297
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(2 boxes)
46 TLS and 1 ALS from Leon Trotsky to Max Shachtman. 17 carbons of letters from Shachtman to Trotsky, including 1 ALS and 16 TLS from Trotsky to third parties, and third party correspondence. Concerns the Communist opposition in the 1930s, especially in the United States.
Shachtman, Max, 1903-1972
Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Hans P. Kraus.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Max Shachtman was born in Warsaw on September 10, 1904 and emigrated to the United States with his family in early childhood. At a quite young age Shachtman was attracted to communism and became a prominent American Marxist and labor activist. He was the author and editor of many books, including Sacco and Vanzetti (1927), Ten Years: The History and Principles of the Left Opposition (1933), and Behind the Moscow Trials (1936). He also co-translated some works by Leon Trotsky and was general editor of the latter's Selected Works (1936). Shachtman's activities dropped off after 1940. He died in 1972.
Along with James P. Cannon and Martin Abern, Max Shachtman split from the Communist Party in late 1928 to found the Communist League of America (Left Opposition), a pro-Trotsky group opposed to the dominant, Stalinist orientation of the Third International. Shachtman, Cannon and Abern immediately founded the newspaper The Militant. After Trotsky's expulsion from the USSR in January 1929, this core group of American Trotskyites entered into direct correspondence with him in an attempt to coordinate the international struggle against Stalinism, which they understood as a bourgeois-nationalist distortion of the internationalist communism of Lenin.
The American Trotskyite movement gained momentum throughout the 1930s through participation in labor disputes and the increasingly unattractive behavior of Stalin. Trotsky's move to Mexico in 1936, after spending 1933-1936 in France and Oslo, Norway, was a powerful stimulus for his American followers. In 1933, they founded the journal The New International. In the late 1930s it engaged in a short-lived merger with the Socialist Party, an experience that left it with the new name of Socialist Workers Party. It was allied with the Trotskyite Fourth International, convened at Paris in 1938. By 1940, Shachtman, along with James Burnham, had soured on the USSR to such a degree that they left the Socialist Workers Party in order to move towards non-Marxist socialism. It was at this point that Trotskyism was struck with the murder of its leader, Leon Trotsky, in his Mexican exile, on August 20 1940.
Scope and Contents
Shachtman's correspondence with Trotsky in Series I: Trotsky to Shachtman and Series II: Shachtman to Trotsky chronicles many of the organizational developments of the American Trotskyite movement. Trotsky often advises Shachtman on the correct position to take in the Trotskyite organs The Militant and The New International. Many letters reflect Shachtman's efforts to publish Trotsky's works, both in these journals and in book form, through publishers such as Boni, and later with the Trotskyite Pioneer Publishers. Trotsky followed the development of an American Opposition movement with great satisfaction and concern, and his letters often contain instructions addressed to individual party leaders. Other topics of discussion include the activities of various communist figures in Germany, England, Spain, and France.
Series III: Letters from Trotsky and Series IV: Other Correspondence and Papers provide a wider perspective on the same fractional combat. Most of the letters from Trotsky in Series III are addressed to the collective of Trotskyite leaders in the US and deal with events of movement-wide significance. The final letter, addressed to the Executive Committee of the Fourth International and dated just six months before his assassination, is a call for party unity in the face of deepening schism. Series IV comprises related correspondence among leading members of the American Trotskyite movement, such as Shachtman, Cannon, and Joseph Hansen.
Militant; New international; a monthly organ of revolutionary Marxism; Socialism -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Cannon, James Patrick, 1890-1974; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999; Hansen, Joseph; Nin, Andrés, 1892-1937; Shachtman, Max, 1903-1972; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940; Communist League of America (Opposition); Communist Party of America; Workers Party of the United States
- Trotsky to Shachtman, 1930 Apr 16; Series I
  - TLS: incl. carbon and TLS dated 1930 Apr 16 to Winitsky (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 2-10)
  - TLS: incl. TL to Boni (publisher) and copy of telegram from Boni dated 1931 Jan 17 with holograph notations, 1931 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
  - TLS: incl. partial English translation, 1931 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - TLS: incl. carbon, 1932 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - TLS: with holograph notation "Harriet Ashbrook", 1932 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - TLS: with notations by Shachtman, 1933 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - TL: incl. copy of TL dated 1933 Aug 22 to James P. Cannon (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - TLS: to the Editorial Board of New International, with notation "Greetings from Trotsky", 1933 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - TLS: signed in Russian, 1934 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - ALS: signed "Crux", 1936 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - TLS: signed "Crux", addressed to Trent, 1936 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - TLS: signed "Crux.", 1937 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - TLS: signed "V. T. O'Brien', addressed to Shachtman, James P. Cannon, Martin Abern and James Burnham, 1937 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - TLS: signed V. T. O'Brien, with notation "LDT's letter", 1939 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - TLS: with TL to Charles Malamuth dated 1939 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - TLS (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
- Shachtman to Trotsky, 1930 Jun 30; Series II
  - TL: 2 copies, 1930 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - TL (Box 1, Folder 49-54)
  - TL (Box 1, Folder 55-59)
  - TL (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - TL (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
- Letters from Trotsky, 1930 Mar 6; Series III
  - Gerard Rosenthal: TLS, 1930 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Frances Gerard: ALS, 1930 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Editorial Board of The Militant: TL, English translation, 1930 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Editorial Board of The Militant: TL, partial English translation, 1930 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Boni (publisher): TL, 1931 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1931 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1931 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Andrés Nin: TL, excerpts, 1931 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, incl. holograph note and English translation, 1931 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - The Central Committee of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1932 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1932 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1932 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Neurath: TL, 1932 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1932 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Albert Glotzer: TL, 1932 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1932 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Arne Swabeck: TLS, 1932 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Arne Swabeck: TLS, 1932 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - The Leadership of the Communist League of America: TLS, incl. TL to Albert Weisbord, 1932 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Unidentified: TL, 1933 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - National Committee of the Communist League of America: TLS, 1933 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Arne Swabeck: TLS, 1934 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Unidentified: TL, "to IS", 1937 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Unidentified: TL, "in re the magazine", 1937 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Adolf: TL, "Copie pour Shachtman", 1937 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - James P. Cannon: TLS, with holograph corrections, 1937 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Mr. Warburg: TL, 1937 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - James Burnham: TL, 1937 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - "Dear Friends": TL, 1939 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - "Dear Comrades": TL, 1939 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - The Executive Committee of the Fourth International: TLS, signed "Crux", 1940 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Address change notice for "Leon Sedoff", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Other Correspondence and Papers, 1937 Jan 5; Series IV
  - Joseph Hansen to Max Shachtman, 1937 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Harold Isaacs to "Dear Comrades", 1937 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Joseph Hansen to James P. Cannon, 1937 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Joseph Hansen to Max Shachtman, 1938 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Lillian Kurtz to Max Shachtman, 1939 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - "Natalia Ivanovna Sedoff (Sedova)": typescript in English, with French holograph notations, [1953] (Box 1, Folder 101)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 8 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Box 1, folder 10 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Box 1, folder 11 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Box 1, folder 14 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Box 1, folder 16 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Box 1, folder 22 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Box 1, folder 25 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Box 1, folder 26 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Box 1, folder 27 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Box 1, folder 30 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Box 1, folder 31 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Box 1, folder 32 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Box 1, folder 33 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Box 1, folder 34 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Box 1, folder 35 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Box 1, folder 36 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Box 1, folder 39 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Box 1, folder 41 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Box 1, folder 46 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Box 1, folder 47 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Box 1, folder 48 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Box 1, folder 49 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Box 1, folder 50 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Box 1, folder 51 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Box 1, folder 52 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Box 1, folder 53 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Box 1, folder 54 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Box 1, folder 56 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Box 1, folder 57 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Box 1, folder 58 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Box 1, folder 58a (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Box 1, folder 69 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Box 1, folder 60 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Box 1, folder 61 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - Box 1, folder 62 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Box 1, folder 63 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Box 1, folder 66 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Box 1, folder 67 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Box 1, folder 68 (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - Box 1, folder 70 (Box 2, Folder 147)
  - Box 1, folder 71 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - Box 1, folder 72 (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - Box 1, folder 73 (Box 2, Folder 150)
  - Box 1, folder 74 (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Box 1, folder 75 (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - Box 1, folder 78 (Box 2, Folder 153)
  - Box 1, folder 79 (Box 2, Folder 154)
  - Box 1, folder 80 (Box 2, Folder 155)
  - Box 1, folder 82 (Box 2, Folder 156)
  - Box 1, folder 83 (Box 2, Folder 157)
  - Box 1, folder 84 (Box 2, Folder 158)
  - Box 1, folder 85 (Box 2, Folder 159)
  - Box 1, folder 86 (Box 2, Folder 160)
  - Box 1, folder 87 (Box 2, Folder 161)
  - Box 1, folder 88 (Box 2, Folder 162)
  - Box 1, folder 89 (Box 2, Folder 163)
  - Box 1, folder 91 (Box 2, Folder 164)
  - Box 1, folder 92 (Box 2, Folder 165)
  - Box 1, folder 93 (Box 2, Folder 166)
  - Box 1, folder 94 (Box 2, Folder 167)